<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conformity with piety, requisite in Gods service Delivered in a visitation sermon at Kingston upon Thames September 8. 1638. By William Hardwick priest and curate of Reigate, in Surry.</title>
            <author>Hardwick, William, priest and curate of Reigate.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4023</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4023)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1207:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conformity with piety, requisite in Gods service Delivered in a visitation sermon at Kingston upon Thames September 8. 1638. By William Hardwick priest and curate of Reigate, in Surry.</title>
                  <author>Hardwick, William, priest and curate of Reigate.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Okes for Richard Cartwright and are to be sold at his shop in Duck-lane next Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4023:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONFORMITY with PIETY, requiſite in GODS Service. <hi>Delivered in a Viſitation Sermon at Kingſton</hi> upon Thames September 8. 1638.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Hardwick</hi> Prieſt and Curate of <hi>Reigate,</hi> in <hi>Surry.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sint unum, Doceant unum, fateantur et unum;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num qui à Chriſti nomine nomen habent.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>I. Okes</hi> for <hi>Richard Cartwright</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Duck lane</hi> next Smithfield. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4023:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4023:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reverend Father in God, VVILLIAM Lord Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane,</hi> Chancellor of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and one of his Majeſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable privy Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Reverend father in God,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Know your <hi>Grace</hi> cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that ſo meane a perſon every way as my ſelfe, and one altogether unknowne to your <hi>Grace,</hi> ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to offer ſo poore a <hi>Sermon</hi> to your ſacred hands: neither am I ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how much this my <hi>ambition</hi> will expoſe me to further <hi>Cenſure:</hi> But God Almighty knowes, 'tis not your <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> but <hi>exemplary Piety</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> which hath imboldned me to ſhroud theſe Papers under your <hi>Graces</hi> Wings. And' tis no ſmall encouragement
<pb facs="tcp:4023:3"/>to me, to heare how ready your <hi>Grace</hi> is, not onely to countenance the <hi>Labours</hi> of the <hi>Learned</hi> of the times, but alſo the meaneſt endeavours of the <hi>pooreſt Prieſts,</hi> who ayme at the <hi>peace of Holy Church,</hi> whoſe <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> next under our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and our <hi>pious Soveraigne,</hi> your <hi>Grace,</hi> to the admiration of all men, continually ſeekes to <hi>Advance.</hi> This your <hi>Graces</hi> Charity towards Others, hath made me to <hi>adventure to</hi> caſt this <hi>Sermon</hi> at your <hi>Graces</hi> feet: which as it aimes at, what your <hi>Grace</hi> delights in, <hi>Piety and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> ſo in all humility it begs your <hi>Paternall Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;</hi> which if it have the <hi>happineſſe</hi> to Obtayne, I doubt not but the <hi>Reader</hi> ſhall find no ſmall <hi>benefit</hi> by it: And I the meaneſt of thoſe who wait on <hi>Gods ſacred Altar,</hi> ſhall daily ſollicite the <hi>throne of Mercy</hi> for your proſperous ſucceſſe in the affaires of the <hi>Church Militant,</hi> that ſo, when you ſhall have finiſhed your Courſe, your <hi>Grace</hi> may be crowned with <hi>glory</hi> in the <hi>Church Triumphant:</hi> and this ſhall ever be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>your Graces in all humility,</hi> William Hardwick.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4023:3"/>
            <head>Conformity with Piety, <hi>Requiſite in Gods Service.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 119. 125.</bibl>
               <q>I am thy Servant, give me underſtanding, that I may know thy teſtimonies.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever he be, Be he of what ſtate or condition ſoever, ſo long as he lives here, he is but a ſervant; and if it be his happineſſe to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Saint in Heaven, He is uſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in with that Title, <hi>Euge bone et fidelis ſerve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.</note> wel done thou good and faithfull ſervant, enter into thy Maſters joy. But here, I muſt confeſſe, we are not a little puzled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the choice of our ſervice; for though in our Baptiſme we did moſt ſolemnly renounce the ſervice of the World, the Fleſh, and the Divell, yet by our practice All of us do declare that we have ſtill a liking to each of them: the Fleſh hath ſome; the World o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: I will not ſay the Divell hath moſt; yet thus much I dare ſay, that they who have wholly given up themſelves to the ſervice of the Fleſh and the World, ſhall at length by woefull Experience finde that <hi>Capiet omnia Daemon,</hi> The Divell will have All.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4023:4"/>Well, though it be thus with moſt, yet the Saints of God have made another choyce: for looke but upon this our <hi>David,</hi> who having had ſome knowledge of the world, and not a little tryal of the fleſh, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times having beene foyled by Sathan, yet by the mercy of God, on the one ſide, and his owne hearty repentance on the other, he frees himſelfe from their (ſervice I will not call it, but) ſlavery. And now finding Almighty God, really to be his God, he binds himſelfe (as it were) Apprentice to him; and as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, ſo here he acknowledgeth himſelfe his, and none but his ſervant: <hi>Servus ego tuus,</hi> I am thy Servant, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you with a large Diſcourſe of the booke of Pſalmes in generall, or of this ſo large and pithy a Pſalme in particular; which, in the judgement of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> excelleth the reſt as fane, is the light of the Sunne exceedes the light of the Moone: I come rather to the Text it ſelfe, uttered by one, who was no leſſe a King than a Prophet: And as hee was a Prophet, and a good Prophet, not unworthy the imitation of us, the ſonnes of the Prophets, and of all thoſe likewiſe who beare any affection or good will, either to Prophets, or Prophets Children.</p>
            <p>In the Words two things offer themſelves to our Conſideration. Firſt, our <hi>Prophets</hi> profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>I am thy Servant.</hi> Secondly, his petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Give mee underſtanding, that I may know thy teſtimonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his <hi>Profeſſion</hi> we are to conſider two things: Firſt, his Condition; <hi>Servus,</hi> he was a <hi>Servant:</hi> Secondly, <hi>cujus,</hi> whoſe ſervant he profeſs'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4023:4"/>to bee, <hi>Tuus,</hi> thy <hi>Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in his petition, we are to conſider the thing prayed for: <hi>Vnderſtanding.</hi> Secondly, the means of attaining it, and that is by way of gift: <hi>Da intellectum,</hi> give mee underſtanding. Laſtly, we have the end why he prayes for this gift of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and that is, that hee may know the teſtimonies of his God. Theſe are the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, which by Gods aſſiſtance, I am come to treate of at this time: Wherefore relying both on your patience and charity, with as much brevity as may be of each of them. Firſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the firſt, our <hi>Prophets Profeſſion,</hi> and in that too firſt of his Condition, <hi>ſervus,</hi> I am a Servant.</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to peruſe the Scriptures, thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles of our God, yee ſhall finde, that it hath ever beene the humble acknowledgement of the Saints, that they are Servants: who, though they have beene advanced in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and ſo diſtinguiſhed from inferiour people, by gracious and honourable Titles, yet with none of them were they more delighted, than with this of Servant: for the preſent, our <hi>Prophet</hi> makes this good: For 'tis not <hi>Rex ego,</hi> or <hi>Propheta ego, I am a King,</hi> or <hi>I am a Prophet:</hi> but <hi>ſervus ego, I am a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi> As much likewiſe appeares by the Apoſtles; who, for the moſt part, aſſume this title of Servant, and in a manner preferre it before that of Apoſtle: for this they uſually mention firſt: as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Paul, a ſervant of Ieſus Chriſt, called to bee an Apoſtle.</hi> So likewiſe 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Simon Peter, a ſervant, and an Apoſtle.</hi> Doubtleſſe, they had no ſmall honour in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4023:5"/>being Apoſtles, but yet their Happineſſe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Greater in being the ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Damnatus Apoſtolorum unus, ſervorum nullus:</hi> One of the Apoſtles was caſt off, never any of Gods ſervants ſo: Thus likewiſe Prophets have bin excluded, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath beene ſhut againſt ſome of them: what though they have thought to juſtifie themſelves with their Lord, Lord, we have propheſied in thy name? Yet this hath not ſerved their turne, for they have beene diſmiſſed with a <hi>Non novi vos, diſcedite,</hi> I know you not, depart from me yee workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. But never were ſervants uſed thus: and therefore in this Title the Saints have taken more comfort, and have had more confidence then in any other: <hi>Servus,</hi> ſaith our Prophet here, I am a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</p>
            <p>Here then taken notice we may of our Condition: what though many of us are preferred to places of Eminency, and to put a luſtre on our Glory, are Graced with Titles anſwerable to our place? yet for all this, 'twill not be amiſſe, amidſt them all, to take this along with us, that we are none other then ſervants likewiſe: yee cannot imagine how this will let out the Apoſtumated matter of Pride, which otherwiſe may ſwell and burſt us. Humane frailty is ſuch, that men are apt to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured of their Advancement, and if they have bin ſo happy, as to gaine a popular applauſe, this their ſuppoſed Happineſſe, if they have not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to keep them under, may proove their ruine and deſtruction: From which fearefull downfall that we may be ſecure, 'twill not (I ſay) be amiſſe, while we are in the height of our Happineſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4023:5"/>now and then upon this our Condition to which we are ſubjected: <hi>Servi ſumus,</hi> we are ſervants.</p>
            <p>But why this here, may ſome ſay: are there any ſo ignorant as not to know this? who ſo ſtupid, as not to acknowledge it? This is the voice of men of all rankes: all men acknowledge themſelves ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: And, your Servant, and at your ſervice are the ordinary Parentheſis of our Diſcourſe: Nay, the whole World is come to that paſſe, that many will not only conclude of themſelves that they are Servants, but alſo in a contemptible manner reflect upon others, and in a ſordid and baſe way uſe many, and thoſe (I may ſay) their betters, none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as Servants, and tis well, if not worſe: ſhould I inſtance in our ſelves, in men of our owne Tribe, 'twill (I feare) be to too apparent. Many of which, though they are ſuch, whoſe Deſerts might challenge an awfull reſpect unto their perſons, yet in the opinion of many none more contemptible, none more deſpiſed then they. We, beloved, with ſuch are <hi>ſerve</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only Servants, yea, Hirelings, nay what not? poore <hi>Micajah</hi> the parſon of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, if he be fed with the bread of Affliction, and with the Water of Affliction; 'tis enough for him: A ſtoole, a Table, and a Candleſticke are a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency: As for Reverence and Reſpect to his perſon, they are Workes of Supererogation, and have beene along ſince baniſhed hence with Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And indeede, thus it hath beene in all Ages. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved as much in his time:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.13.</note> Wee are (ſaith hee) made the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the World, and the of-ſcouring of al things.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4023:6"/>Thus, ſhould we deſcend to this preſent day, and trace the times as Hiſtorians have recorded them, we ſhould finde even the choyceſt of Gods <hi>Prophets,</hi> by many accounted no better. I am ſure for the preſent, none more cenſured, none more neglected, none more vilified, none more ſlighted in many places, than we of the Clergy be. And as for that Title wherewith Almighty Ged hath beene plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to grace us: that ſame Title of ours (I ſay) is not mentioned but in deriſion: every ignorant and prophane wretch hath the name of <hi>Prieſt</hi> in his mouth, which with a kinde of ſcumme hee caſts into the faces of thoſe, who profeſſe this ſacred function: nay farther, ſuch is the impudency of the Age, that he now a dayes is accounted a Wit of the times, who Libells, or envies moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fathers of the Church: the beſt of whom, are in the account of theſe men, none other than meane ſervants; not as <hi>David</hi> here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged himſelfe, but in their owne phraſe and meaning, an unworthy, an undeſerving generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the world could better ſpare than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profeſſion whatſoever. But to ſtoppe the mouthes of ſuch prophaners of God, his ſervants, and his Ordinances, let them but take along with them the <hi>Cujus,</hi> the next thing to be conſidered, and then, though ſervants we be, yet not Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of ſo ſmall account, as they would willingly have us, being we are ſervants onely of our God: <hi>ſervus tuns,</hi> I am thy ſervant, that's the next.</p>
            <p>A ſervant (yee ſee) this our Prophet was, but not every ones: 'tis <hi>ſervus tuns.</hi> Indeede, in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4023:6"/>we may be rearmed your Servants, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels themſelves are: But this ſervice of theirs and ours to you, is but a branch of that ſervice which wee owe unto our God.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.5.</note> We preach (ſaith the Apoſtle) not our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord; and our ſelves your ſervants, for Jeſus ſake: ſo that all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice we doe to you, is with reference to our Lord and Maſter, Chriſt Jeſus; none otherwiſe we owe, none otherwiſe we performe: Almighty God is our Maſter, and his ſervants the Saints have onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt themſelves to be. <hi>David</hi> here would adhere to none other, none other Maſter would he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: <hi>Tuns,</hi> I am thine.<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> I have found <hi>David</hi> my Servant, (ſaith God) with much holy Oyle have I annoynted him. There God had choſen <hi>David,</hi> wherefore <hi>David,</hi> as in other places, ſo here, to ſhew what liking he had to his Maſter, profeſſeth himſelfe to be his Servant; <hi>ſervus tuns,</hi> I am thy Servant.</p>
            <p>Now this was his reference to God, to bee his Servant; and indeede not a man living, but in a ſort may be ſaid to be Gods ſervant. But yet there are ſome who are ſervants in a nearer kind: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe whom he hath ſet on worke to ſome choiſe and notable deſignement, either in the Church, thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. That hee was a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt, ſet apart to the preaching of the Goſpell, or in the Common-wealth: Thus is this our Prophet marked out, (as I ſhewed you but now) I have found <hi>David</hi> my ſervant: Now theſe are not onely Gods Subjects, over whom hee rules <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by generall command, as a King: but they are alſo men of his Houſhold, whom he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4023:7"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by ſpeciall power, as a Maſter: ſo that in this reſpect, <hi>David,</hi> and other, the Saints of God, whom hee publickly imployes in his ſervices, in a ſpeciall manner are tearmed his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>Hence then we may ſee both our Dignity, and our Duty: our Dignity firſt, in that we are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Gods Servants in ſuch a manner. Should any of us bee entertain'd as Servants to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, how would wee thinke our ſelves graced? how honoured? Why behold, beloved, He whom we ſerve is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and one, at whoſe feete all the Princes, and mighty ones of the earth muſt caſt their Scepters. Why therefore ſhould any of us bee dejected, having ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? certainely, if our Conſciences can aſſure us, that our God called us to ſerve at his Altar, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be happy, wee cannot but bee honourable. What though ſome Curriſh <hi>Doegs</hi> maligne the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and endeavour to bring them into contempt? yet God and good men will ever honour them, and hat for their workes ſake. And truely our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, for the better entertainment of his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage brought by us, hath ever graced us with Noble Titles: though we in Humility are to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelves, with this our <hi>Prophet,</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: yet our God will have us reputed as his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and as ſhining Starres; yea, as Angels. Thus hath he (whatſoever the world thinkes to the contrary) provided for us, who are imployed in this ſo ſacred a buſineſſe, as the Miniſtery is; nay, not the meaneſt of his ſervants ſhall be neglected; our Saviour ſaith as much:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.26.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4023:7"/>
            <p> The conſideration of which in the next place ſhould put us in minde of our Duty. <hi>Servus eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men officij:</hi> the very name of ſervant implies ſome duty to bee performed. Wherefore if yee pleaſe to call to mind what yee expect of your ſervants, yee may in a manner perceive, what God requires of you.</p>
            <p>Now two things there are, which we principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend in our ſervants; Obedience and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: idle and ſawcy ſervants wee account unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the meaneſt wages. Why, beloved, the ſame our God requireth of us, both <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> all of us muſt be obedient, all of us muſt be Reverent. We that are his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> muſt ever be in a readineſſe to do our Maiſters ſervice; ſo that when he ſhall be pleaſed to acquaint us with his will, and ſhall commaund us to feede his flocke, and to tell <hi>Iudah</hi> her ſinnes, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> her tranſgreſſions: we muſt not then linger like <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> nor loiter by the way, now framing one excuſe, then another: But to our buſineſſe wee muſt goe, our taske we muſt take in hand, be it never ſo hard, never ſo difficult: knowing that there is a <hi>Vae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Icre. 48.10.</note> a woe unto thoſe who do the worke of the Lord negligently, or with Saint <hi>Paul, Vae mihi ſi non Evangelizavero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> Woe unto me if I preach not the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And no leſſe a curſe hangs over the head of the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if they be negligent: for as we of the Clergy muſt ſhew our obedience to our Maiſter by declaring his will to you, ſo muſt you ſhew your obedience by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting your ſelves to the will of <hi>God,</hi> not onely hearing, but doing of his word: It reſts in you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4023:8"/>to obey the forme of Doctrine which yee are taught, when with the <hi>Bereans</hi> yee have ſought and found it to be true, and no way repugnant to Holy Writ. Oh, beloved, when your conſciences tell you, that yee are guilty of ſuch ſinnes, which yee heare at any time taxed in the Pulpit, whether they be ſinnes of blood, or ſinnes of uncleanneſſe, or ſins of diſcontent, ſinnes of muttering and murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the God of Heaven, and his Vice-Gerent here on earth: In a word, whatſoever ſinnes they be, your obedience cannot better be ſhewed, than by your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for that which is paſt, and your pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendment for the time to come; all which are the true ſignes of obedience, and by which alone the ſervants of God are diſcovered really to be his.</p>
            <p>Neitheir is here all; beſides our Obedience, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence alſo is expected. Thus much we expect from our ſervants, and thus much God expects from us; as <hi>Mal. 1.6.</hi> If I be a Father, where is mine Honour? If I be a Maſter, where is my feare? ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. Who is he amongſt us, that hath the ſpirit of a man within him, that will ſuffer his ſervant to bee Haile-fellow with him, to ſit cheeke by jole by him, or to ſit covered in his preſence? now, cannot we brooke this diſ-reſpect in our ſervants, be they never ſo faithfull? and thinke ye that our God, when wee are performing any part of his ſervice, eſpecially when we are here in his houſe, his preſence Chamber; thinke ye (I ſay) that our God will take this our male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part behaviour well at our hands? What do ye talke of Gods requiring onely our hearts? ye are miſtaken, God requireth as well our Hats, our Knees, and our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4023:8"/>whole bodies: ſurely if God requireth our hearts, which are our chiefeſt parts wherewith we doe him ſervice, he doth then comprehend all the reſt, which are inferiour and leſſe noble.</p>
            <p>But alas, theſe he ſhall hardly get of any of us, in theſe ſo nice and wanton times: The practices of too too many confirme this, whoſe irreverence in the Holy Aſſembly is ſo apparant, as if they had none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceite of their God, than that he is an Idoll of the Heathens, which hath eares, and heares not; eyes, but ſee not: Here, here in the Church (with griefe of ſoule I ſpeake it) we, may to too often diſcover ſome laughing, others prating; ſome Courting, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers barganing, ſo that St. <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> complaint may well be taken up in theſe dayes:<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>24.</hi> in Act.</note> 
               <hi>Alios video ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; nugari, dum preces fiunt; neque ſolùm dum preces fiunt, ſed &amp; dum ſacer dos benedicit: neſcis quod cum Angelis ſtas? cum illis cantas? cum illis hymnos dicis? &amp; ſtas Ridens? non mirum eſſet, ſi fulmen emittere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur non ſolùm in eos, ſed etiam in nos, digna enim ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſunt hae.</hi> Some (ſaith he) I behold trifling or toying, when others at prayers; and not onely thus in prayer time, but alſo when the Prieſt is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the bleſſing: what, knoweſt thou not that thou ſtandeſt with Angels? and that thou ſingeſt Hymnes and Pſalmes with them? and ſtandeſt thou laughing? It were no wonder, if thunder ſhould be caſt, not onely on thoſe, but alſo on us, for theſe things, ſuch irreverence as this deſerveth ſuch a judgement. And againe the ſame Father: <hi>Stat ſacerdos Dei orationem offerens cunctorum; tu autem rides, nihil timens non contremiſcis? non collegis teipſum: in anlam Regiam intraturus, &amp; habitu &amp; oculis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4023:9"/>&amp; inceſſu componis te &amp; exornas: Huc antemin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traturus, ubi eſt Aula Regis coeleſtis, rides, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ambulas, negotiaris.</hi> Gods Prieſt ſtands offering up the prayers of the people, and what doeſt thou laugh, fearing nothing? What doeſt thou not tremble? doeſt thou not recollect thy ſelfe? Wert thou to enter into the Kings Court, thou wouldſt have a care both of thy Habite, and thy whole carriage, but when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt hither, where the Court of the King of Heaven is kept, thou laugheſt, thou talkeſt, thou walkeſt, and art otherwiſe uncivilly buſied. But what (thinke ye) is the cauſe of this irreverence of ours? if you pleaſe, I will tell you what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive:</p>
            <p>There is a Concluſion highly cryed up amongſt us, and which hath oftentimes beene objected to me, and 'tis this: That Churches are none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ordinary and common places, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in time of Divine Service. For my part, I confeſſe ingenuouſly, I cannot but bluſh to heare ſuch an unſavoury aſſertion to proceede from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mouth, which makes a profeſſion of Chriſt and Chriſtian Religion: Oh Beloved, ſhall we who are Chriſtians, belch out that againſt the Houſe of our God, which never any Pagan did againſt the Temple of his feigned Deity? Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Brethren! are not theſe Houſes alwayes ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to a holy uſe? ſet apart to a holy imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? doe not ſinnes of Theft, or of uncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. committed in them, appeare with a farre more ghaſtly and horrid countenance, than if they had beene committed in other places?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4023:9"/>In a word, when wee ſet our feete on theſe ſacred pavements, doe not theſe ſtones we tread on, put us in minde of our duty, as that we have holy thoughts, holy geſtures? 'Twere a happineſſe, not to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, could we at all times, and in all places have holy thoughts of our God: which, becauſe our weakneſſe is ſuch that we cannot, Almighty God hath appointed ſet times, and ſet places for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming theſe holy Duties. Now the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Gods publick worſhip, is the Church; now, what a Church is,<note place="margin">Hom. 36. in 1. Cor.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tells us: <hi>Non eſt Eccleſia tonſtrina, aut vnguentaria taberna, aut Officina forenſis; ſed locus Angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Regia Coeli, Coelum ipſum.</hi> The Church is no Barbers or Apothecaries ſhop, 'tis no <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> or <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> but the place of Angels, the Court of Heaven, yea, Heaven it ſelfe: into the which when the Saints heretofore entered, what proſtrations, what incurvations did they uſe? Oh how they did bedew the pavements with their Teares! Thus reverent were the Saints, the Servants of God, in the Houſe of their gracious Maſter. And indeede, why ſhould they not? for Nature it ſelfe teacheth no leſſe; Never Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan entred into the Temple of his Idoll, but with Reverence, and what now? Shall Idols have this, and not the Living God? ſhall Heathens bee reverent, and not Chriſtians? Let no man torture himſelfe with a cauſeleſſe feare of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition in being thus Reverent, in the holy Aſſemblies. Indeede, were our Reverence ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to the walles, or to ſome Image, or Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, or the like, there were too apparent cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4023:10"/>of feare; but whereas our Reverence is tendered onely to God himſelfe, I ſee no reaſon at all in the world, why wee ſhould not uſe all Reverence that poſſible may be in this Houſe of God. Wherefore, ye that are fearefull of Superſtition, let me deſire you to be as fearefull of prophaneſſe; fall not into the one, by flying from the other. Now for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to tread in Gods Courts, without putting of their Hats, bending their bodies, bowing their knees, and other the like geſtures of Reverence, if this be not outward prophaneſſe, I ſeriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I know not what prophaneſſe is.</p>
            <p>Yea, but may ſome ſay, This outward Reverence may ſhelter much hypocriſie, and therefore why ſhould it bee ſo much urged, as now a dayes it is?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer,</hi> ſuppoſe it doth; ſuppoſe, many may draw neare to God with their lips, when their hearts are farre from him; as alſo ſit here with their heads uncovered, when their Hearts are at home ſhut up in their cheſts, or otherwiſe gone after their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe; what of all this? ſhall (ſay I) the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of ſome make others irreverent? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid: For my part, when I come into a Church, and there behold a poore ſinner kneeling upon his knees, weeping with his eyes, and with an humble and lowly Reverence both petitioning and hearing his God, my charity bids me thinke the beſt, as how that theſe ſhewes are not without ſubſtance, becauſe I know no other; it being a peculiar priviledge and prerogative of Almighty God to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a knower, a ſearcher of the Heart: But againe, let me ſee a man here
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4023:10"/>ſitting in his Maſters Houſe, in his Maſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as if he were rather God Almighties fellow, than his Servant, ſeldome uncovering his head, ſeldomer bending his knee, or ſawcily lolling on his Elbowes: let ſuch a man make never ſo many proteſtations that his heart is upright to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I ſhall hardly bee brought to beleeve him: for if there were any zeale, any Reverence in the inward man, it would appeare, and ſhew it ſelfe in the outward man. Well, I ſay no more but this, know that ye are Servants, and then ye cannot but be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ye cannot but be reverent.</p>
            <p>One thing more I have to commend unto you from this Title of <hi>Servant,</hi> before I leave it, and 'tis this:</p>
            <p>Servants (ye ſee) we are all of us; now ſervants can never performe their buſineſſe well, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendably, unleſſe they agree together: where there is contention amongſt ſervants, that Houſhold is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes our of order, and the Maſter of ſuch a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffereth very much thereby himſelfe. Why juſt thus it is in this great Family, the Common-wealth; thus 'tis like wife in the Church: where there is not Unity, Unanimity, and Conformity amongſt us the Servants of God, amongſt us the Stewards of God, and diſpencers of his Word, all things goe to wrack. I would to God therefore, that there were that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amongſt us, as ought to be amongſt thoſe, who ſerve one God, and profeſſe one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: Happy would it be for you of the Laity, and no leſſe happineſſe would redound to us of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Doubtleſſe ſuch unſavoury Compariſons would not then be ſo often heard at your Table, I am for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4023:11"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and another, I am for <hi>Apollos;</hi> I am for this Preacher, and I am for that. The cauſe of all which, is aſwell the want of Conformity amongſt The Teachers, as want of ſtayedneſſe amongſt the Hearers: O, when it comes once to this paſſe, that—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scinditur incerius ſtudia in contraria Clerus.</hi> When we of the Clergy ſhall be full of oppoſitions, ever and anon banding one againſt another, and thinking ſcorne to be Ruled or Directed by thoſe, who are the Fathers of the Church, I mean the moſt reverend Arch-biſhops, and the right reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: when we ſhall diſagree amongſt our ſelves: yea, when ſome of us ſhall not agree with our ſelves, but be this day of another minde, than we were yeaſterday, and in this place than in that; and all this oftentimes not for Conſcience ſake, but policy: conforming in the Univerſity, and ſubſcribing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhop, but ſounding out an Alarum of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiance to all ſuch regularity and orders when they are ſent amongſt the people; accounting the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church indifferent amongſt the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as being not able to anſwer them; but crying out amongſt the vulgar that the zeale of the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-hood muſt by no meanes tolerate. Now ſay I, what other thing proceedes from this non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and Multiplicity of Contradictions, but Contentions and Heart-burnings in every place? This double-dealing hath bred in many ſimple men and women, yea, ſome of them are ſuch, who (I am perſwaded) have an earneſt deſire to feare GOD, and are ſuch who tremble at his ſacred word: yet ſuch Religious ſoules as theſe have a doubtfull wavering when they enter into
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4023:11"/>the Church, whether they may kneele, when others kneele; or pray, when the Miniſter reades Prayer; or heare the Sermon, when a conformable Prieſt poth preach; or whether they may bow at the ſacred name of Jeſus, or ſuffer their Children to be baptized with the ſigne of the Croſſe, with a hundred ſuch like: In a word, whether they may come to Church on Wedneſdaies and Fridayes, and ſuch like times, when there is no Sermon. Thus,<note place="margin">W. Weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>B.D.</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons <hi>Porch.</hi>
               </note> halting guides (ſaith a learned Divine of ours) have begot limping Schollers. The Church is diſturbed, our prayers hindered; one ſwelieth againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one ſpeaketh evill againſt another, one judgeth another; and all this, becauſe there is not that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and unity as ſhould be amongſt thoſe, who, with <hi>David</hi> here, profeſſe themſelves the ſervants of Almighty God.</p>
            <p>But now, doe yee deſire to have all redreſt? as indeed, which of us ſhould not? Why then doe yee, (I beſeech you) as this our Prophet did, who, as hee profeſt himſelfe the ſervant of God, ſo hee now ſues unto him for that, which may make his ſervice acceptable, and what other is that, than under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? which leades me to my ſecond branch; his <hi>Petition:</hi> and in that, firſt to the bleſſing prayed for: <hi>Vnderſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have here (yee ſee) much fruit to gather, and but a little more time allotted: that therefore which remaines I will husband as well as I can, that ſo yee may have ſome taſte of all.</p>
            <p>That which the eye is to the Body, the ſame is underſtanding to the ſoule. A Body without eyes can ſee nothing, and a ſoule without underſtanding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4023:12"/>can judge of nothing, This is that therefore that <hi>David</hi> prayes for: <hi>Da intellectum,</hi> Give mee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. And indeed if Vnderſtanding bee needfull for any, then ſurely for a Prophet, a chiefe part of whoſe Office, is to bee a guide to the blind, and to inſtruct thoſe that are ignorant and voyde of Vnderſtanding: All which, how can hee poſſibly doe, who wants this gift of Vnderſtanding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed <hi>David;</hi> what neede hadſt thou to pray thus for Underſtanding? Hadſt thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in theſe dayes, the leſſe knowledge, the leſſe underſtanding thou hadſt had, the better hadſt thou beene accepted amongſt many, or elſe how comes it to paſſe that poore ignorant Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks are ſo highly ſet up, and ſo often cryed up, as the onely zealous Preachers, and Rebukers of ſinne: with ſuch Admirers of ignorance, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the moſt part, are but Time-ſervers, or Court Flatterers. But now, if ſuch <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> as theſe, can make their tongues now as nimble, as their Shuttle was heretofore, then wee crye out ſtraight way <hi>Digitus Dei;</hi> Surely, theſe men were ſent from Heaven; though what they deliver be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: for the moſt part but railing; and the maine part of their Tautologicall and tedious Diſcourſe, tend to the upholding ſuch a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as this, that they are the beſt Chriſtians, who are the worſt Subjects. Such (Teachers I will not ſay but) Bablers, if they have enough of Impudence, care not how little of Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But our <hi>Prophet</hi> (yee ſee) heere was of another minde; underſtanding hee wanted,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4023:12"/>underſtanding he ſues for, <hi>Da intellectum,</hi> give mee Vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>But what? had he no underſtanding at all? yes, <hi>habebat intellectum</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>ſed ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundare ſibi crederet, uberiorem inquirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Loc.</note> Hee had underſtanding, but he deſires a larger meaſure ofit, thereby intimating thus much unto us, that, while wee are cloathed with the ragges of our Mortality, there is no hope of an abſolute perfection in this ſo Noble a faculty of the ſoule: And therefore they who fancy that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all things, may juſtly bee ſuſpected to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nothing as they ſhould. This our <hi>Prophet,</hi> v. 100. profeſs'd that hee had more underſtanding than his Teachers: and yet behold hee had not ſo much, but that he wants more, and more here hee prayes for: And 'tis St. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Advice, on this my Text, <hi>Nunquam intermittenda eſt iſta petitio</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>non enim ſufficit acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſe intellectum, &amp; Dei Teſtimonia didiciſſe, niſi ſemper accipiatur, &amp; quodammodo ſemper bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur de fonte lucis aeternae.</hi> This Petition ought alwaies to bee had in remembrance, for 'tis not ſufficient to have received underſtanding, and to have learned the Teſtimonies of God, unleſſe we alwaies receive, and after a ſort continually drinke of the Fountaine of eternall Light. And to ſay the truth, the benefit that will redound to us hereby, ſhould make us ever mindfull of the Petition: for as all miſchiefe attends on Ignorance, ſo all happineſſe waites on Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding. If this bee not ſo, I appeale to this Learned Audience. Bleſſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4023:13"/>Fathers and Brethren, what is the cauſe now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, I pray you, of all the diſcontents and jarres in our Church, but want of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? Men void of underſtanding are apt to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Fury for Zeale, and Superſtition for Devotion: Oh how prone are we to accuſe the actions of our Brethren, which we underſtand not? Thus <hi>Papiſts</hi> deale with us on the one ſide, and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts</hi> on the other. Firſt, they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> crye out, that we are utter enemies to Mortification, being we have baniſhed (as they ſay) all meanes tending thereunto, as Faſting, Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and other the like workes of Humiliation: But yee that are judicious know all this to be falſe, and that all this is a meere ſlander; for they underſtand us not. Indeed, we teach you that yee are not to put any merit in Faſting; but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we affirme and account it to bee an excellent helpe unto Devotion, and ſo according to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles given at theſe Viſitations, we acquaint you with thoſe times of Faſting, which are appoynted by the Church. So likewiſe for Confeſſion, our Church is ſo farre from being an enemy to it, that (though we doe not make it a picke-locke of the State) we uſe it as a Cordiall for afflicted Conſciences; and ſo are wee directed in our <hi>Rubricke</hi> for the Viſitation of the ſicke; where likewiſe is ſet downe a forme of Abſolution to be pronounced by the <hi>Prieſt</hi> upon hearing the Confeſſion of his Poenitentiary. Thus in divers others other particulars could I inſtance, would the time permit, wherein they ſhamefully tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us, &amp; that, becauſe they underſtand us not. And againe no leſſe fouly doe our <hi>Amſterdamians</hi> fal upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4023:13"/>us with bitter Invectives, accuſing us for our harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, revered, and ſignificant Ceremonies; which did they but truely underſtand, I am very confident they would be farre better affected towards us. So that ye ſee the neceſſity of underſtanding, and that for men of all Ranks, both Prieſts and people; little charity can be ſhewed the one to the other without it: which now if ye have a deſire to attaine, be yee but pleaſed to follow me with this our Prophet, and he will ſhew you the <hi>modus</hi> how to procure it: Doe ye pray, God will give it; 'tis his gift; that's the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; <hi>Da intellectum,</hi> Give me underſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Intellect us ſpirituale munus eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Loc</note> (Ambr.) <hi>&amp; ideo quod Dei eſt, à Domino poſtulatur:</hi> Underſtanding is a ſpirituall gift, and therefore what is Gods pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, is ſought for at Gods hands. So St. <hi>Hierome, Ate diſcam, &amp; non ab Haereticis &amp; Judaeis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Loc.</note> I will neither learne of Hereticks or <hi>Jewes,</hi> neither of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers nor Humaniſts; Thou onely O Lord, ſhalt be my Teacher: And this is none other than what is recorded in Holy Writ. Doubtleſſe, ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> in the Booke of <hi>Job, there is a ſpirit in Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 32.8.</note> 
               <hi>but the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth underſtanding.</hi> Were it from Nature, all would have it; or were it incident to Old age, ancient men could not want it; or if Labour could procure it, the diligent might abound with it. <hi>Surely</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 28.1, 2</note> 
               <hi>there is a veyne for the Silver, and a place for Gold where they fine it: Iron is taken out of the Earth, and Braſſe is molten out of the ſtone, &amp;c. But</hi> verſe 12. <hi>where is Wiſdome to be found? where is the place of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding?</hi> Hee anſwers, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. <hi>GOD onely knoweth the way thereof. If therefore any of you lacke Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4023:14"/>ſaith Saint <hi>James, let him aske of God, and it ſhall be given him.</hi> A man may read much, hee may heare much, he may converſe much; but if God doe not open the eyes of the Intellect, if he doe not cleare the Underſtanding, he ſhall groape even at Noone-day: And as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> on my Text, <hi>Parum prodeſset Legem in auribus noſtris ſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, vel ſcriptam oculis noſtris proponi, &amp; hominis voce enarrari, niſi correcto noſtro ſtupore, intus nos Deus arcano Spiritus ſui inſtinctu dociles redderet.</hi> It ſkills little either to heare or read the Law, unleſſe Almighty God by the ſecret inſtinct or Inſpiration of his Holy Spirit make us docile, and capable of his Heavenly Counſell. If therefore thy Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding bee over-clouded with the vapours of Errour of Ignorance, downe then on thy knees to thy God, and touch not a Booke or a Paper, till thou haſt made thy way by ſome pious Ejaculation or other: And then, if thou findeſt the ſucceſſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thy deſire, bleſſe God for it, and be not thou proud of what thou haſt attained; for what thou haſt, is Gods gift; whether it bee the gift of Tongues, or the gift of Propheſie, or what other gift ſoever; each of them, all of them deſcended from the Father of Lights: Hee was the giver of it, and none elſe.</p>
            <p>And withall, I would have you take notice, that as God gives underſtanding, ſo he gives it ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by meanes: To us of the Clergy by Prayer and ſtudy; and to you of the Laity, uſually by our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry: ſo that, if yee doe not frequent the publick Aſſemblies, and ſeeke for underſtanding and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from the lips of the Prieſts, yee may thanke
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4023:14"/>your ſelves, if yee continue ignorant ſtill: Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſeemes to intimate as much here; for the word which hee uſeth for <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> in the Originall ſignifies as well the place, where they were to bee learned, the Congregation, as the Teſtimonies themſelves: ſo that <hi>David,</hi> as hee would learne them, ſo hee would learne them in the right <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi;</hi> not in private Conventicles, where he might have heard <hi>Anarchy</hi> cryed up as the ready way to peace and Piety; but in the publicke Aſſemblies, in the Congregation, in the holy Sanctuary of his God.</p>
            <p>And oh that once we could learne to ſee our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe! the Happineſſe wee enjoy in theſe Times! Oh how ought we to bleſſe our God, who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us freedome to come into his Courts, no <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Inquiſition, no Lawes or Edicts to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: All the Lawes we have are to compell us, and to puniſh us for not comming hither; and for our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encouragement to frequent the Courts of our God, ſuch hath beene the Piety of our Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, and the care of the vigilant Fathers of our Church, that for the bettering of our Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they have put life againe into that meanes, which a long time hath laine (as it were) in a dead ſleepe amongſt us. And if yee would know what that is, 'tis Catechizing; without which all our other Labours are in vaine: 'tis that which muſt cleare the eyes of the Vulgar and Common people; without it, underſtand certainely they cannot: Where this Catechizing is not uſed, preach wee may, yea, and <hi>Ad Clepſydram</hi> too, but heere's the miſchiefe of it; all our Preaching will have no better ſucceſſe than this, wee ſhall but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4023:15"/>preach you into ignorance. But <hi>Manum de Tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la;</hi> enough of this for the preſent: A word or two of the laſt Branch, the end why hee prayeth thus for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and I have done.</p>
            <p>The end (yee ſee here) is <hi>That hee may know the Teſtimonies of his God;</hi> and no marvell that hee deſires to have an inſight in them; for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe infinitely excelleth all other Learning whatſoever. In humane Learning a Devill in Hell doth wonderfully ſurpaſſe the beſt Proficients a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men; but this Knowledge of the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of God, and of his mercy to us in Chriſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto us in them, ſurpaſſeth the comprehenſion of any Angell of darkneſſe whatſoever: for it is the Spirit of God onely which knoweth the things of God; and therefore here let us fixe: and that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we have in all other Arts and Sciences, let us uſe as a Hand-maid unto this.</p>
            <p>But yet here is not all; there is a knowledge of Practice, as well as of Judgment required of us; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia</hi> as well as <hi>Scientia</hi> is expected:<note place="margin">De Inter. Dom. c. 12.</note> 'Tis a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of Saint <hi>Bernards, Multi quaerunt Scientiam, panci Conſcientiam;</hi> Many are inquiſitive after Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, few after Conſcience. <hi>Siverò tanto ſtudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſolicitudine quaereretur Conſcientia, quanto quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſecularis &amp; vana Scientia, &amp; citius apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur, &amp; utilius retineretur:</hi> But if Conſcience were with as great ſtudy and care ſought after as vaine and worldly Science is, it would bee both ſooner obtained, and with farre more profit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Let every man therefore looke to his Conſcience, to his Life, to his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: If wee that preach, and yee that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4023:15"/>profeſſe Religion, be careleſſe of theſe, woe worth the time that ever wee were borne; for that ſame knowledge that wee have of the Lawes and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of our God, ſhall be ſo farre from excuſing, that it ſhall accuſe us rather. <hi>He that knows his Maſters will, and doth it not,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>ſhall be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with many ſtripes:</hi> And no marvaile, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Maſter ſeemes to be very much ecclypſed by ſuch diſorderly ſervants.</p>
            <p>I remember devout <hi>Salvian</hi> brings in the Pagans inſulting over the Chriſtians, whoſe lives were not agreeable to their knowledge.<note place="margin">De Guber. Dei. l. 4.</note> 
               <hi>In nobis</hi> (ſaith that Father) <hi>Chriſtus patitur opprobrium, in nobis Lex Chriſtiana patitur maledictum:</hi> Both Chriſt and his Law are ſcandalized by us: <hi>De nobis enim dicunt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gani, Ecce quales ſunt Chriſtiani, qui Chriſtum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt?</hi> Behold, this is the common report of Pagans concerning us: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eſt Lex Catholica quam credunt? vbi ſunt Pietatis &amp; Caſtitatis praecepta quae diſcunt?</hi> Where is this Catholick Law which they beleeve? where are theſe precepts of Piety and Chaſtity, which they learne? <hi>Evangelia legunt, &amp; impudici ſunt; Apoſtolos audiunt, &amp; inebriantur; Chriſtum ſequuntur, &amp; rapiunt; vitam improbam agunt, &amp; probam Legem habere ſe dicunt.</hi> They read the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpells, and yet are uncleane; they heare the Apoſtles, they frequent Sermons, and yet are Drunkards; they follow Chriſt, and yet are Theeves; they lead a wicked life, and yet they boaſt that they have a righteous Law. But now, if ye pleaſe, yee ſhall heare what theſe Heathen people inferre and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude upon all this; <hi>Falſum planè eſt quod aiunnt ſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na diſcere, quod jactant ſe ſanctae Legis praecepta re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4023:16"/>ſi enim bona diſcerent, boni eſſent.</hi> 'Tis altogether falſe (ſay they) that they learne good things, and as they boaſt, that they reteine the Rules of a holy Law; for if thoſe things which they learne were good, they then would be good themſelves. Thus doe we, who would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, bring our God, our Religion, our Profeſſion into contempt, if our lives bee not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to our knowledge.</p>
            <p>Which, I would to God, every one of us would take into our conſideration, that ſo at length wee may bee carefull to adorne our Profeſſion by our more than ordinary Piety. And as for thoſe who will ſtill be refractory, ye that have the Rod of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in your hands, let them ſmart for it: Beare it not (I beſeech you) in vaine, but ſmite, and ſmite home; wee muſt preach, but 'tis you that muſt puniſh. And as for you who are Church-wardens, and ſworne Officers to doe God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſervice in his Church, looke yee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to your Oaths: 'Tis Gods cauſe, not your owne, which yee are ſworne to defend. And therefore let Whore-maſters, and Drunkards, and prophaners of the Lords Day, and blaſphemous Swearers, and ſuch like lewd livers be brought to feele the Diſcipline of our Mother <hi>Holy Church,</hi> whoſe Doctrine they have ſo much diſparaged by their unholy lives. Certainely, if ever the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> or <hi>Roman Tongue</hi> deſerve to be tearmed the Language of the Beaſt, 'tis when Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens come in with their <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> whereas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſwearing and whooring, and ſuch like diſorders keepe their Rendevous in their Pariſh;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4023:16"/>this one word more, and I have done: Be ye care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I beſeech you, of your Duty, as we will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be of ours, and then our Gracious God thereby will be glorified, our Brethren e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, and our owne ſoules eternally ſaved, at the Day of the Appearing of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Concionem hanc ſuper illud 119. 125. typis mandari permitto.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa. Baker.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lond.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 6.</hi> 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
